Andre De Coppet Collection, 1566-1936 (bulk 1770-1865 ): Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
- Jefferson, Thomas (1743-1826), 1776-1826; 3 boxes (1 partial)
  - Correspondence, 1776 July 8-1826 March; 2 boxes (1 partial)
    - Gerry, Elbridge, 1802 August 28; 1 item (Folder 26)
      ALS, Monticello. Citing suspicious accounting as the reason Gerry's brother was removed from office; explaining how certain officers from the previous administration were also removed in order to make room for republican appointees. 2 pp.
    - Harrison, Benjamin, 1781-1784 May 7; 1 folder
      Harrison was a Virginia delegate to the Continental Congress and Governor of Virginia from 1781 to 1784.
      - Harrison, Benjamin, 1781 January 1; 1 item (Folder 27)
        ALS (RC), In Council. Reporting the arrival of a British fleet in [Chesapeake] Bay, suspected to be hostile; asking for advice from the General Assembly. Docketing on the back notes that the letter was laid on the table by the Assembly. 1 p. [Vol. 4: 289-290]
      - Harrison, Benjamin, 1784 May 7; 1 item (Folder 27)
        ALS (RC), Annapolis. Sending news of Congress and the topics it will address including treaties of commerce, Indian affairs, and western posts. Answering a question about loan office debt. Discussing how many states have yet to adopt the impost. 2 pp. [Vol. 7: 225-6]
    - Hatch, Frederick W, 1825 July 6; 1 item (Folder 28)
      ALS (RC), in third person. Forwarding tuition fees of Benjamin and Lewis Randolph [sons of his daughter, Martha]. 1 p.
    - Humphreys, David, 1784 June 21-1794 January 3; 3 folders
      - Humphreys, David, 1784 June 21; 1 item (Folder 29)
        ALS (RC), Boston. Transmitting his decision to postpone a trip to France as the only ships currently available would expose him to an undesirable "crowd of passengers," mentioning that Mrs. [John] Adams and her daughter recently left on a crowded ship, and saying that the next time he sees Humphreys he will deliver a packet of papers from General Washington. 1 p. [Vol. 7: 311-12]
      - Humphreys, David, 1784 June 27; 1 item (Folder 29)
        ALS (RC), Boston. 8 o'clock P.M. Hastily notifying Humphreys that Mr. Tracy, whose ship is bound for London, has agreed to stop at France; urging Humphreys to immediately come to Boston as the ship leaves in a matter of days. 1 p. [Vol. 7: 321]
      - Humphreys, David, 1784 July 4; 1 item (Folder 29)
        ALS (RC), Boston. 6 o'clock P.M. Regretting that Humphreys was unable to join him for the passage to Paris, suggesting alternate travel plans, requesting that Humphreys board with him once he reaches Paris. With mention of Dr. [Benjamin] Franklin at Passy. 1 p. [Vol. 7: 363-4
      - Humphreys, David, 1786 March 14; 1 item (Folder 29)
        ALS, London (RC). Responding to Humphreys' resignation as secretary to the commissions, commending and thanking him for his service, asking him to write with news from America and deliver a letter to [John] Jay. 1 p. [Vol. 9: 328]
      - Humphreys, David, 1786 May 7; 1 item (Folder 29)
        ALS (RC), Paris. Mentioning some business he has undertaken following Humphrey's resignation, discussing the terms of commercial treaties with Portugal and Prussia, the hostility of England towards the U.S., and the anticipated death of the King of Prussia. 2 pp. [Vol. 9: 469]
      - Humphreys, David, 1786 August 14; 1 item (Folder 29)
        ALS (RC), Paris. On the poor state of the public treasury; Algerian, Moroccan, and European affairs; his work with the Marquis de Lafayette to secure a commercial treaty; and painter [John] Trumbull's visit to Europe. 2 pp. [Vol. 10: 250-252]
      - Humphreys, David, 1790 August 11; 1 item (Folder 29)
        ALS (RC), New York. Giving detailed orders for Humphreys to travel to London, Lisbon, and Madrid to deliver letters & papers and meet with specific individuals, with a warning that he should do his best to appear as a private traveler. 2 pp. [Vol. 17: 125-7]
      - Humphreys, David, 1791 March 15; 1 item (Folder 29)
        ALS (RC), Philadelphia. Informing Humphreys that he has been appointed Resident Minister at the court of Lisbon, giving the title of a book, enclosing an act meant to reduce England's power at sea [not included], and providing directions for various communications and financial transactions. 3 pp. [Vol. 19: 572-4]
      - Humphreys, David, 1791 April 11; 1 item (Folder 29)
        ALS (RC), Philadelphia. Partly in cipher with interlinear deciphering. Complaining about Mr. Carmichael's failure to keep the U.S. government apprised of his actions and intelligence; directing Humphreys and [William] Short to carefully procure information on Brazil without provoking suspicion from the Court of Lisbon; sending various papers [not included]. 2 pp. [Vol. 20: 209-210]
      - Humphreys, David, 1791 April 11; 1 item (Folder 29)
        ALS (RC), Philadelphia. Marked "Private." Ordering a book of letters by Cortez and a history of Christopher Columbus; discussing samples of wine shipped from Lisbon. 1 p. [Vol. 20: 210-211]
      - Humphreys, David, 1791 May 2; 1 item (Folder 29)
        LS (RC), Philadelphia. Introducing the bearer, John Wilcocks, Jr. 1 p.
      - Humphreys, David, 1791 May 13; 1 item (Folder 29)
        LS (RC), Philadelphia. Announcing that Thomas Barclay has been appointed U.S. Consul at Morocco, giving instructions to Humphreys concerning Barclay's salary and governmental funds at his disposal. Included is a copy of a letter to bankers Willink, Van Staphorts, & Hubbard, and the official instructions sent to Thomas Barclay. [Vol. 20: 397-400, 406-7]
      - Humphreys, David, 1791 July 13; 1 item (Folder 30)
        LS (RC), Philadelphia. Concerning the provisioning and ransoming of a group of captives at Algiers, with their names; briefly mentioning the war with the Indians, the National Bank, and the President. 4 pp. [Vol. 20: 624-5]
      - Humphreys, David, 1791 July 26; 1 item (Folder 30)
        ALS (RC), Philadelphia. At the request of Robert Morris, inquiring whether William Duncan is being held captive at Algiers. [He was not, see Vol. 20: 677-8 for more.]
      - Humphreys, David, 1791 November 29; 1 item (Folder 30)
        ALS (RC), Philadelphia. Briefly touching on many topics including war against the Indians, the Negro insurrection at St. Domingo, the soon-to-be-published census, legislative action, and domestic manufactures; with directions regarding Humphreys' post as diplomat. 2 pp. [Vol. 22: 353-4]
      - Humphreys, David, 1791 December 13; 1 item (Folder 30)
        LS (RC), Philadelphia. Instructing Humphreys to investigate and pay Don Joseph Torino a sum of money for the Count de Espilles, who put out money for American captives at Algiers. 1 p. [Vol. 22: 400]
      - Humphreys, David, 1792 April 9; 1 item (Folder 30)
        ALS (RC), Philadelphia. Briefly reporting on many topics including war with the Indians, General St. Clair's resignation, failures of stock jobbers, a Congressional bill concerning state representation, the insurrection at Haiti, and negotiations at Madrid. 2 pp. [Vol. 23: 386-7]
      - Humphreys, David, 1792 July 12; 1 item (Folder 30)
        ALS (RC), Philadelphia. Saying that he is traveling to Virginia (following the President), reporting that Vermont is attempting to extend its boundary nearer to British posts, hoping for peace with the Indians. 1 p. [Vol. 24: 221]
      - Humphreys, David, 1792 November 6; 1 item (Folder 30)
        ALS (RC), Philadelphia. On dealings with the Indians and the condition of agriculture; with a lengthy postscript complaining about Portugal's possible prohibition of American wheat and corn products, questioning how Portugal would respond if America decided to ban their wines. 2 pp. with separate half page postscript saying that the letter will be sent directly to Lisbon and not through London. [Vol. 24: 587-8]
      - Humphreys, David, 1792 November 8; 1 item (Folder 30)
        ALS (RC), Philadelphia. Marked "Private." Notifying Humphreys of his intention to resign as Secretary of State, sending news of peace with the Wabash and Illinois Indians. 1 p. [Vol. 24: 595-6]
      - Humphreys, David, 1793 January 2; 1 item (Folder 31)
        ALS (RC), Philadelphia. Sending papers and plans for the city of Washington, D.C. [not included], reporting the result of elections and an upcoming treaty meeting with the Western Indians, and inquiring about the grain market. 2 pp. [Vol. 25: 8-9]
      - Humphreys, David, 1793 March 21; 1 item (Folder 31)
        LS (RC), Philadelphia. Giving directions for Humphreys to travel to Gibraltar to deal with Moroccan affairs and handle diplomatic business in the wake of the deaths of [John] Paul Jones and Mr. Barclay; appointing Nathaniel Cutting as Humphreys' secretary. 3 pp. [Vol. 25: 420-422]
      - Humphreys, David, 1793 March 22; 1 item (Folder 31)
        ALS (RC), Philadelphia. Strongly urging Humphreys to negotiate with Portugal to accept U.S. flour; insisting on the preservation of neutrality should a general war break out in Europe, asking for new from various nations, and sending some confidential papers and letters to be forwarded [not included]. 2 pp. [Vol. 25: 426-7]
      - Humphreys, David, 1793 March 22; 1 item (Folder 31)
        ALS (RC), Philadelphia. Marked "Private." Saying his resignation has been slightly delayed but will occur within the year; giving a lengthy explanation of his efforts to get Captain O'Brian out of Algerian captivity; and expressing frustration that [William] Carmichael, diplomat to Spain, has sent but one letter in three years. 3 pp. [Vol. 25: 427-9]
      - Humphreys, David, 1793 March 30; 1 item (Folder 31)
        ALS (RC), Philadelphia. Writing a shorter version of his March 21, 1793 letter to Humphreys (giving directions for completing business in Algiers) as a vessel is sailing directly to Lisbon and can carry the letter. 1 p. [Vol. 25: 468-9]
      - Humphreys, David, 1793 April 12; 1 item (Folder 31)
        ALS (RC), Philadelphia. Asking Humphreys to delay drawing on the full amount of a bill so as not to entirely deplete the funds for foreign legations; saying that [Nathaniel] Cutting has been delayed due to the outbreak of war between France, Great Britain, and Holland. 1 p. [Vol. 25: 532]
      - Humphreys, David, 1793 April 26; 1 item (Folder 31)
        LS (RC), Philadelphia. Announcing the President's proclamation of neutrality, discussing how Humphreys should proceed should Portugal become involved in the war, and forwarding a copy of the letter of neutrality sent to various foreign ministers [included] 1 p. and 2 pp. respectively. [Vol. 25: 587-8]
      - Humphreys, David, 1793 September 11; 1 item (Folder 31)
        ALS (RC), Philadelphia. Describing the Yellow Fever epidemic and continued disagreements with the Indians. 1 p. [Vol. 27: 90]
      - Humphreys, David, 1794 January 3; 1 item (Folder 31)
        ALS (RC), Philadelphia. Announcing his resignation as Secretary of State and the appointment of [Edmund] Randolph in his place. [Copies of this letter were sent to various U.S. diplomats]. 1 p. [Vol. 28: 4-5]
    - Huntington, Samuel, 1791 December 29; 1 item (Folder 32)
      LS (RC), Philadelphia. Forwarding various acts [not included]. 1 p.
    - Jackson, Andrew, 1819 November 22; 1 item (Folder 33)
      ALS (RC), in third person, Monticello. Thanking him for a copy of the vindications of the proceedings in the Seminole War. 1 p.
    - Lambert, William, 1809 September 10; 1 item (Folder 34)
      ALS (RC), Monticello. Commending Lambert on his scientific endeavors including fixing a meridian for the country and a projected publication. With harsh words for the British Constitution, declaring it "the most corrupted & corrupting mass of rottenness which ever usurped the name of government." 2 pp. [Retirement Series, Vol. 1: 511-512]
    - Lee, Richard Henry, 1776 July 8; 1 item (Folder 35)
      Letter (copy), Philadelphia. Sending a copy of the declaration of independence, mentioning his plans to travel to Virginia and his wish for a successor. 1 p. [Vol. 1: 455-6; an accompanying copy of the declaration can be found in the Documents folder]
    - Lee, Thomas Sim, 1780 June 14; 1 item (Folder 36)
      ALS with subscription and postscript in Jefferson's hand (RC), Richmond. Planning a line of express riders to relay timely and confidential information between northern and southern posts; with mention of the expected arrival of the French fleet. 2 pp. [Vol. 3: 444-445]
    - Legaux, P, 1802 April 1; 1 item (Folder 37)
      ALS, Washington. Written in third person. Thanking Legaux for a bundle of grape vine plants to be sent to Monticello. 1 p.
    - Mansfield, Jared, 1803 July 18; 1 item (Folder 38)
      ALS (RC), Washington. Concerning the expenses of Mansfield's trip to Washington and a monetary advance for his surveying instruments, arranged by [Albert] Gallatin. 1 p.
    - McCulloch, James H, 1816 October 9; 1 item (Folder 39)
      ALS (RC), Monticello. About the importation of two cases of wine, with directions for future imports of books & wines from Europe. 1 p.
    - Mercer, James, 1778 June 14; 1 item (Folder 40)
      ALS (RC), Albemarle. Asking Mercer to verify the amount of a debt and send any news of the British army and French intervention. 1 p. with docketing and a note by Mercer on back. [Vol. 2: 199]
    - Mifflin, Thomas, 1793 December 21; 1 item (Folder 41)
      ALS (RC). Clarifying confusion over a group of French sailors in the jail at Philadelphia; saying they are technically in the custody of the Judiciary authority and therefore the Executive will not interfere. 1 p. [Vol. 27: 605]
    - Minor, John, 1805 December 20; 1 item (Folder 42)
      ALS, Washington. Forwarding a letter of Thomas Paine [not included], asking Minor to inquire whether the Virginia legislature might help him. 1 p.
    - Monroe, James, 1816 April 17-1822 September 5; 1 folder
      - Monroe, James, 1816 April 17; 1 item (Folder 43)
        ALS (RC), Poplar Forest. Asking Monroe to forward a letter of condolence to the daughter of his late dentist, Dr. Thomas Bruff. 1 p.
      - Monroe, James, 1822 September 5; 1 item (Folder 43)
        ALS (RC). To the President. Breaking his rule of not asking government officers for favors as a Mr. Patrick Gibson of Richmond greatly needs help. 1 p.
    - Morris, Gouverneur, 1793 August 16-1802 March 21; 1 folder
      - Morris, Gouverneur, 1793 August 16; 1 item (Folder 44)
        Letter (copy), Philadelphia. A lengthy letter outlining the inappropriate behavior of Edmond Charles Genet, French minister to the United States, who repeatedly refused to respect U.S. neutrality. 43 pp. [Vol. 26: 697-715]
      - Morris, Gouverneur, 1802 March 21; 1 item (Folder 44)
        ALS (RC), Washington. About final payment to sculptor [Jean Antoine] Houdon for a statue of [George] Washington. 1 p.
    - Newton, Thomas, 1802 February 2; 1 item (Folder 1)
      ALS, written in third person. Ordering four barrels of cider, arranging for shipment and safe payment. 1 p.
    - Nicholas, Wilson Carey, 1801 October 25; 1 item (Folder 2)
      ALS, Washington. Saying it is up to the Senate to accept the treaty [with Napoleon], giving an update on Rufus King's work in London, complaining about incidents at the Spanish port of Algeciras, with mention of Louisiana and the census. 1 p.
    - Nicholson, Joseph H, 1807 February 20; 1 item (Folder 3)
      ALS (RC), Washington. About the Burr conspiracy, mentioning [James] Wilkinson, [John] Adair, Ogden, and [Henry] Dearborn. 1 p.
    - Page, John, 1784 November 11-1802 February 20; 1 folder
      - Page, John, 1784 November 11; 1 item (Folder 4)
        ALS, Paris. Sending the letter through Colonel Le Maire with news of European politics, a report on animal magnetism [not included], and some phosphoric matches; asking for news from the assembly. 2 pp. [Vol. 7: 514-5]
      - Page, John, 1802 February 20; 1 item (Folder 4)
        ALS (RC), Washington. Asking for the contents of the letter to remain secret. Saying the U.S. mint will likely be suppressed by Congress, reporting that too many of the general government offices are filled by Virginians, and asking whether Page might be interested in taking the collectorship at Petersburg as Colonel Heath must be removed from the post due to his temper and "the fury of his federalism," discussing the duties and salary of the position. 2 pp.
    - Patterson, John, 1819 January 31; 1 item (Folder 5)
      ALS (RC), Monticello. Expressing joy over the passage of the university bill, discussing the qualifications of a professor, giving family news, and awaiting the arrival of Italian stonecutters. 1 p.
    - Peale, Charles Wilson, 1808 November 15; 1 item (Folder 6)
      ALS. Suggesting a course of study for his grandson while in Philadelphia including Peale's museum, [William] Hamilton's garden, and surgical operations; agreeing to exchange polygraphs in the hopes that Peale can fix his. 1 p.
    - Peyton, Craven, 1803 September 7; 1 item (Folder 7)
      ALS, Monticello. About the registration of a deed for a mill in Kentucky. 1 p.
    - Pinckney, Thomas, 1792 November 20-1793 March 15; 1 folder
      U.S. Minister at London.
      - Pinckney, Thomas, 1792 November 20; 1 item (Folder 8)
        ALS (RC), Philadelphia. Forwarding a letter addressed to the Governor of Pennsylvania, with instructions on patronage. 1 p. [Vol. 24: 646]
      - Pinckney, Thomas, 1792 December 3; 1 item (Folder 8)
        ALS (RC), Philadelphia. Marked "Private." On the result of Congressional elections and the rise of republicanism, saying that he expects Adams to be elected Vice President despite opposition. 2 pp. with detached address sheet. [Vol. 24: 696-7]
      - Pinckney, Thomas, 1793 March 15; 1 item (Folder 8)
        LS, Philadelphia. To Pinckney and [Gouverneur] Morris. Giving directions for U.S. ministers to encourage and aid in the liberation of the Marquis de Lafayette. A postscript in Jefferson's hand notes that [David] Humphreys was also sent a copy. 1 p. [Vol. 25: 387-9]
    - Plumer, William, 1810 July 12-1816 July 21; 1 folder
      - Plumer, William, 1810 July 12; 1 item (Folder 9)
        ALS, Monticello. Concerning Plumer's intention to write a history of the United States; offering any information in his possession with the warning that he has no papers or records beyond his correspondence and his own memories. Commenting on the rise of Federalism in 1808. 1 p. [Retirement Series, Vol. 2: 505-506]
      - Plumer, William, 1816 July 21; 1 item (Folder 9)
        ALS (RC), Monticello. Responding to a printed speech of Plumer's; discussing the inviolability of institutions and the want of economy in the English government. 1 p.
    - Read, Jacob, 1784 November 11; 1 item (Folder 10)
      ALS (RC), Paris. Reviewing European affairs and the prospects of war between various nations, characterizing England as "totally absorbed in self interest," discussing the treaties he is negotiating and the U.S. debts to France and Holland. 2 pp. with docketing by Read on the back. [Vol. 7: 515-6]
    - Remsen, Henry, 1795 March 11; 1 item (Folder 11)
      ALS (RC), Monticello. Thanking Remsen for sending gongs and a threshing machine, discussing his own establishment of a nail manufactory. 1 p. [Vol. 28: 304-5]
    - Roane, Spencer, 1822 May 31; 1 item (Folder 12)
      ALS, Monticello. Asking Roane to provide his legal opinion of a financial situation that Jefferson fears may bankrupt him. 2 pp. Manuscripts explaining the details of the case are included: a draft and a polygraph copy of AMs labeled "The case of the exrs of W.C. Nicholas with Morrison, and of the same with Owings," 4 pp. each, and a draft and polygraph copy of AM entitled "Abstracts from sundry Documents in the case of the Exrs of W.C. Nicholas with Morrison and of the same with Owings," 4 pp. each. [The Nicholas in question is Wilson Cary Nicholas.]
    - Rodney, Caesar A., 1808 April 24-1815 March 16; 1 folder
      - Rodney, Caesar A., 1808 April 24; 1 item (Folder 13)
        ALS, written in third person. Concerning the expected effects of the U.S embargo on European nations. 1 p.
      - Rodney, Caesar A., 1815 March 16; 1 item (Folder 13)
        ALS (RC), Monticello. Describing his continued frustration with the attitude and actions of England; remarking on embargo laws and the homespun movement; urging a visit. 3 pp.
    - Short, William, 1790 August 26; 1 item (Folder 14)
      LS (RC), New York. Partly in cipher with interlinear deciphering. Concerning certain specifics of the treaty with France, describing a Mr. Campbell who presented himself and claimed to be a minister from Denmark but had no authenticating papers, and writing in code about the payment of the debt to France. 7 pp. [Vol. 17: 431-5]
    - Stackelberg, Baron de, 1822 October 23; 1 item (Folder 15)
      ALS (RC), Monticello. Asking for information about the abilities of a Mr. Runnels, an applicant for a consular appointment. 1 p.
    - Stuart, Josephus Bradner, 1817 February 8; 1 item (Folder 16)
      ALS (RC), Monticello. Pleased to hear the principles of navigation he submitted in 1793 are finally being considered; discussing the future and hopeful prospects of Richmond; commenting on his old age and the youth who now take over the country. 1 p.
    - Teackle, Littleton Dennis, 1826 March 31; 1 item (Folder 17)
      ALS (RC), Monticello. Thanking him for material related to the establishment of primary schools in Maryland, discussing the educational system in Virginia. 1 p.
    - Ternant, Jean Baptiste de, 1793 April 23; 1 item (Folder 18)
      LS, Philadelphia. To Messrs Ternant, [F.P.] Van Berkel, and [George] Hammond [foreign ministers]. Forwarding a copy of the President's proclamation of neutrality [not included]. 1 p. [Vol. 25: 583-4]
    - Washington, George, 1790 August 8; 1 item (Folder 19)
      AL, written in third person. Forwarding secret state papers for revision and approval, and questioning whether it might be "safe and useful" to share certain papers with [William] Short and the Marquis de Lafayette. 1 p. [Vol. 17: 120-1]
    - White, Thomas Willis, 1824 January 7; 1 item (Folder 20)
      ALS (RC), Monticello. Discussing the advisability of reprinting Baxter's History of England a new digest of Coke Littleton printed by Thomas. 1 p.
    - Willink, Van Staphorst & Hubbard, 1791 July 13-1793 March 20; 1 folder
      Bankers at Amsterdam.
      - Willink, Van Staphorst & Hubbard, 1791 July 13; 1 item (Folder 21)
        LC, Philadelphia. Asking them to honor any bills of David Humphreys relating to the maintenance of captives in Algiers. 1 p. [Vol. 20: 626-7]
      - Willink, Van Staphorst & Hubbard, 1793 March 20; 1 item (Folder 21)
        ALS, Philadelphia. Concerning drafts for [Thomas] Pinckney, Nathaniel Cutting, and David Humphreys. 1 p. [Vol. 25: 413-4]
    - Zane, Isaac, 1778 February 26-1783 November 8; 1 folder
      Zane conducted the Marlboro Iron Works in Frederick County, Virginia.
      - Zane, Isaac, 1778 February 26; 1 item (Folder 22)
        ALS (RC), Monticello. Planning for the payment and pick-up of iron pans (used to obtain salt from seawater), mentioning the relative success of the draft, and asking whether Zane might part with his spirit level. 1 p. [Vol. 2: 174-5]
      - Zane, Isaac, 1783 November 8; 1 item (Folder 22)